{
  "reference_number": "12833",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "On balance, I support setting a 2050 target in legislation now. Setting a target will promote political accountability, clarity, and long-\n term certainty. There are, however, some good reasons to seek advice from the Climate Commission about the 2050 target. In\n\n particular, it might be a good idea to ask the Commission to provide expert advice on complicated parts of the 2050 target, such as\n the “sustainable level” for short-lived greenhouse gases. Setting separate targets for the different greenhouse gases is an option\n that should be considered by the new Climate Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I support a 2050 target which is ambitious, clear, and science-based. Accordingly, I support the most ambitious option: net zero\n emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050. However, not all gases are equal. Science recognises the difference between long-\n lived greenhouse gases (such as carbon dioxide and nitrous oxide) and short-lived greenhouse gases (such as methane). I support\n\n a differentiated approach to managing these two groups. Therefore, achieving a net zero 2050 all gases target would mean:\n Combining the mitigation of long-lived gas reductions with carbon sinks (through forestry and carbon sequestration in soil) to achieve\n negative long-lived emissions by 2050; and Reducing short-lived gases to low, sustainable levels. This would balance out to net zero\n\n across all gases, but in the most impactful way possible. Short-lived gases do not need to be reduced to net zero to stop\n temperature rise. They only need to be stabilised. New Zealand should aim for a sustainable level of short-lived emissions which fits\n\n with the Paris Agreement goals to keep global warming well below 2C, striving to 1.5C. Long-lived emissions, however, contribute to\n global warming until they are reduced all the way to zero. Because these gases exist in the atmosphere for millennia, finding ways to\n absorb more of these gases from the atmosphere than the amount we are emitting (known as “negative” emissions) is the most\n\n ambitious and impactful contribution New Zealand could make to counteract global warming. Accordingly, the Zero Carbon Act\n should prioritise reducing long-lived emissions to net zero, and then to negative emissions, by 2050 or sooner."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I support NZ reducing emissions domestically - not using international carbon credits to contribute towards emissions reductions .\n\n Domestic reductions are an investment in our own economic and social development as we transition to a carbon neutral future.\n Relying on international carbon credits (even if the credits have integrity) creates uncertainty about what reductions need to be\n achieved in New Zealand and doesnt create the right signals to business and others about their activity. I prefer a transparent\n\n approach which separates international contributions from our domestic Zero Carbon Act targets. This would not stop New Zealand\n from purchasing international carbon credits as an additional contribution to global mitigation efforts. Purchasing credits helps other\n countries finance their transition to a zero carbon economy, especially developing countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should only be revised in exceptional circumstances. The purpose of the Zero Carbon Act is to provide\n accountability, certainty and flexibility. It will provide accountability and certainty by setting clear, legally-binding emission reduction\n targets. It will retain flexibility by permitting different governments to use different policies to meet these targets, in response to\n\n changing circumstances and new technology. Despite the importance of accountability and certainty, there are some situations\n where it is appropriate to change the 2050 target. For example, if there is a significant change in scientific knowledge or international\n law (such as the Paris Agreement becoming more ambitious). Any revision should require input from the Climate Commission and\n\n approval by Parliament. I do not support being able to revise the 2050 target in response to “economic changes”. The opportunity\ncost of investing now in transitioning will be significantly higher the longer we delay."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support this proposal. Legally-binding budgets, set 10-15 years in advance so that three budgets are in effect at all times, at a level\n\nrecommended by the Climate Commission and approved by Parliament, are a cornerstone of the Zero Carbon Act."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "I don't support budgets being changed. Budgets should only be revised in exceptional circumstances. If an incoming government\n\nwas able to alter the budget, it would create too much uncertainty and instability. A new government can introduce different policies\nto meet the upcoming target"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Under exceptional circumstances, yes. For example, it might be appropriate to change an upcoming budget after an extreme natural\ndisaster (such as a major earthquake). Revising a budget in this situation would not mean changing the long-term 2050 target."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I generally agree with the proposed list of considerations to take into account when setting emission budgets: scientific knowledge\n\nabout climate change technology relevant to climate change economic circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the\ndecision on the economy and the competitiveness of particular sectors of the economy fiscal circumstances and, in particular, the\n\nlikely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing social circumstances and, in particular, the likely\nimpact of the decision on fuel poverty energy policy and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on energy supplies and the\n\ncarbon and energy intensity of the economy the government’s obligations under the Treaty of Waitangi the three government\nobjectives for climate change policy: sustainable economy, global and local leadership and creating a just and inclusive society"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the Zero Carbon Act having a strict time frame for setting out policy plans. This time frame should be 6 months after an\nemission budget has been set."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. For an explanation of these principles, see the section above about “Zero Carbon Act\n\nprinciples”."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. I support the Climate Commission having two functions: (a) providing expert advice, and (b) monitoring our progress and holding\nthe government to account. The Commission should not be a decision-making body."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I generally agree with the proposed list of expertise which should be collectively held by the Climate Commission: climate change\npolicy (including emissions trading) resource economics and impacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) te\n\nTiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori interests climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori\nexperience with addressing adaptation challenges like planning, insurance and local government risk management engineering\nand/or infrastructure community engagement and communications. Desirable, but non-essential, expertise could include: business\n\ncompetitiveness knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system. Missing from this proposed list\nis expertise in public health. A further consideration is that, if adaptation is included in the Zero Carbon Act (see Q14), it will be\n\nimportant to think carefully about how many Commissioners should have adaptation-specific, and working with communities,\nexpertise. It might be a good idea to have a separate committee which focuses on adaptation issues, as is the case in the UK."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. Generation Zero supports the government being required to prepare a national climate risk assessment, and a national policy\n\nplan to address these risks. A monitoring and reporting framework is also important. Local Councils should be involved in these\nprocesses."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I support NZ taking responsibility for our global emissions and the climate impacts that we have contributed to. It’s very important that\n\nall New Zealanders have their say on how we make the shift to a zero carbon future here in New Zealand but we must also help the\nworld’s most vulnerable communities across the Pacific adjust to the impacts on climate change. To ensure that the Zero Carbon Bill\nis transparent, I support the Bill including a requirement to produce annual reports about New Zealand’s international climate change\n\ncontributions in order to ensure that the Pacific countries get the support they need and can plan to adapt to their changing\nenvironment."
    }
  ]
}
